<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<GameData>
	<EnglishText>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_NAME">
			<Text>Globe Theatre</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_DESCRIPTION">
			<Text>+1 [ICON_Amenities] Amenities in all cities that have an Amphitheater. Contains 2 slots for Great Works of Writing [ICON_GreatWork_Writing]. 1 free Great Writer appears near the city where the wonder was built (if one is available).  It must be built on Grassland, Plains or Tundra next to a River.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_QUOTE">
			<Text>"Good, my lord, will you see the players well bestowed? Do you hear, let them be well used; for they are the abstract and brief chronicles of the time: after your death you were better have a bad epitaph than their ill report while you live."[NEWLINE]–Hamlet Act II, Scene 2.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Built in 1599 AD on Maiden Lane in London by the Lord Chamberlain's Men, the theatrical company of which William Shakespeare was a shareholder, the Globe Theatre incorporated a number of design innovations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2">
			<Text>In 1613 the Globe burned to the ground after the thatched roof was set alight by cannonfire during a production of Henry VIII; it was rebuilt on the same site in 1614 and continued in operation until closed by the Puritans in 1642. Although its exact dimensions are unrecorded, it is known that the Globe Theatre was a three-story, circular, open-air amphitheater roughly 30 meters (100 feet) in diameter and able to seat about 300 spectators.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3">
			<Text>The stage was 13 meters (43 feet) wide, 8 meters (27 feet) deep and raised five feet off the ground, allowing for trap doors.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_DANTE_NAME">
			<Text>Dante Alighieri</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_NAME">
			<Text>John Donne</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_MOLIERE_NAME">
			<Text>Molière</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>John Donne (22 January 1572 – 31 March 1631) was an English poet and cleric in the Church of England. He is considered the pre-eminent representative of the metaphysical poets. His works are noted for their strong, sensual style and include sonnets, love poems, religious poems, Latin translations, epigrams, elegies, songs, satires and sermons. His poetry is noted for its vibrancy of language and inventiveness of metaphor, especially compared to that of his contemporaries. Donne's style is characterised by abrupt openings and various paradoxes, ironies and dislocations. These features, along with his frequent dramatic or everyday speech rhythms, his tense syntax and his tough eloquence, were both a reaction against the smoothness of conventional Elizabethan poetry and an adaptation into English of European baroque and mannerist techniques. His early career was marked by poetry that bore immense knowledge of English society and he met that knowledge with sharp criticism. Another important theme in Donne's poetry is the idea of true religion, something that he spent much time considering and about which he often theorized. He wrote secular poems as well as erotic and love poems. He is particularly famous for his mastery of metaphysical conceits. Despite his great education and poetic talents, Donne lived in poverty for several years, relying heavily on wealthy friends. He spent much of the money he inherited during and after his education on womanising, literature, pastimes, and travel. In 1601, Donne secretly married Anne More, with whom he had twelve children. In 1615 he was ordained deacon and then Anglican priest, although he did not want to take Holy Orders and only did so because the king ordered it. In 1621, he was appointed the Dean of St Paul's Cathedral in London. He also served as a member of Parliament in 1601 and in 1614.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_DANTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Durante di Alighiero degli Alighieri, commonly known by his pen name Dante Alighieri or simply as Dante (c.1265 – 1321), was an Italian poet during the Late Middle Ages. His Divine Comedy, originally called Comedìa and later christened Divina by Giovanni Boccaccio, is widely considered the most important poem of the Middle Ages and the greatest literary work in the Italian language.In the late Middle Ages, most poetry was written in Latin, making it accessible only to the most educated readers. In De vulgari eloquentia (On Eloquence in the Vernacular), however, Dante defended the use of the vernacular in literature. He would even write in the Tuscan dialect for works such as The New Life (1295) and the Divine Comedy; this highly unorthodox choice set a precedent that important later Italian writers such as Petrarch and Boccaccio would follow.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_MOLIERE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1">
			<Text>Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, known by his stage name Molière (baptised 15 January 1622; died 17 February 1673), was a French playwright, actor and poet, widely regarded as one of the greatest writers in the French language and universal literature. His extant works include comedies, farces, tragicomedies, comédie-ballets and more. His plays have been translated into every major living language and are performed at the Comédie-Française more often than those of any other playwright today. His influence is such that the French language itself is often referred to as the "language of Molière".</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_1_NAME">
			<Text>Devotions upon Emergent Occasions</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_2_NAME">
			<Text>Songs and Sonnets</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_2_NAME">
			<Text>Paradiso</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_1_NAME">
			<Text>Inferno</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_1_NAME">
			<Text>The Misanthrope</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_2_NAME">
			<Text>Tartuffe</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_1_QUOTE">
			<Text>No man is an island entire of itself; every man is a piece of the continent, a part of the main; any man's death diminishes me, because I am involved in mankind. And therefore never send to know for whom the bell tolls; it tolls for thee.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_2_QUOTE">
			<Text>We can die by it, if not live by love, and if unfit for tombs and hearse our legend be, it will be fit for verse; and if no piece of chronicle we prove, we'll build in sonnets pretty rooms; as well a well-wrought urn becomes the greatest ashes, as half-acre tombs, and by these hymns, all shall approve us canonized for Love.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_2_QUOTE">
			<Text>Here powers failed my high imagination: but by now my desire and will were turned, like a balanced wheel rotated evenly, by the Love that moves the sun and the other stars.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_1_QUOTE">
			<Text>As little flowers, which the chill of night has bent and huddled, when the white sun strikes, grow straight and open fully on their stems, so did I, too, with my exhausted force.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_1_QUOTE">
			<Text>If everyone were clothed with integrity, if every heart were just, frank, kindly, the other virtues would be well-nigh useless, since their chief purpose is to make us bear with patience the injustice of our fellows.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_2_QUOTE">
			<Text>Those whose conduct gives room for talk are always the first to attack their neighbors.</Text>
		</Row>
	</EnglishText>
	<LocalizedText>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_NAME" Language="es_ES">
			<Text>Globe Theatre</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_QUOTE" Language="es_ES">
			<Text>"Y vos, mi buen señor, ¿podéis aseguraros de que los comediantes reciban buen hospedaje? ¿Me oís? Tratadlos bien, porque a su cargo está representar breve y esencialmente las crónicas de nuestros tiempos. Más os vale un mal epitafio que un retrato poco lisonjero en una de sus comedias."[NEWLINE] - Hamlet Acto II, Escena 2.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="es_ES">
			<Text>Construido en el año 1599 en Maiden Lane, en Londres, por Lord Chamberlain's Men, la compañía teatral de la que William Shakespeare era accionista, el Globe Theatre incorporó un gran número de innovaciones en su diseño.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2" Language="es_ES">
			<Text>En 1613, el Globe se incendió hasta los cimientos después de que su techo de paja prendiera debido al fuego de un cañón durante la representación de Enrique VIII. Se reconstruyó en el mismo sitio en 1614 y siguió funcionando hasta que los puritanos lo cerraron en 1642. Aunque no hay constancia de sus dimensiones exactas, se sabe que el Globe Theatre era un anfiteatro de tres plantas circulares y al aire libre de unos 30 metros de diámetro y capaz de acoger a unos 300 espectadores.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3" Language="es_ES">
			<Text>El escenario tenía 13 metros de ancho por 8 de profundidad y se levantaba metro y medio del suelo, lo que permitía el uso de trampillas.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_NAME" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Globe Theatre</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_DESCRIPTION" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>+1 [ICON_Amenities] Annehmlichkeit in allen Städten mit einem Amphitheater. Enthält zwei Plätze für Große Schriftwerke [ICON_GreatWork_Writing]. 1 freier Großer Schriftsteller erscheint neben der Stadt, in der das Wunder errichtet wurde. Muss auf Grasland, Ebene oder Tundra errichtet werden und an einen Fluss angrenzen.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>"Lieber Herr, wollt Ihr für die Bewirtung der Schauspieler sorgen? Hört Ihr, laßt sie gut behandeln, denn sie sind der Spiegel und die abgekürzte Chronik des Zeitalters. Es wäre Euch besser, nach dem Tode eine schlechte Grabschrift zu haben als üble Nachrede von ihnen, solange Ihr lebt."[NEWLINE]– Hamlet, 2. Aufzug, 2. Szene.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Globe Theatre ist der Name eines elisabethanischen Theatergebäudes am Südufer der Themse in London, welches vor allem durch Aufführungen von William Shakespeares Werken einen bedeutenden Platz in der Theatergeschichte einnimmt. Es wurde 1599 erbaut und im 20. Jahrhundert an alter Stelle rekonstruiert. Auch mehrere moderne Nachbauten dieses Theaters in London und an anderen Orten tragen den Namen Globe.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_2" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Das Theater wurde am 29. Juni 1613 durch ein Feuer vernichtet, das während einer Aufführung des Stücks Heinrich VIII. ausbrach, als eine Kanone abgefeuert wurde und das strohgedeckte Dach in Brand setzte. Sehr aufwändige Aufführungen voller realistischer Zutaten waren damals durchaus die Regel. Das Theater wurde aber schon bald wieder aufgebaut, diesmal mit Ziegeldach und im Juli des folgenden Jahres eröffnet. Im Jahr 1642 schloss die puritanische Regierung alle Vergnügungsstätten und somit auch die Theater. Das Globe stand leer und wurde 1644 abgerissen. An seiner Stelle baute man Mietshäuser, und der ursprüngliche Standort dieses bedeutenden Theaters wurde vergessen, bis 1989 im Rahmen von Bauarbeiten Reste des Fundaments wiederentdeckt wurden.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_WONDERS_PAGE_BUILDING_GLOBE_THEATRE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_3" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Das Besondere, und der größte Unterschied zu den heutigen Theatern, besteht wohl, abgesehen von der ungewöhnlichen Bauform, in der großen Nähe zwischen Zuschauern und Schauspielern. Kein Platz war mehr als 20 Meter von der Bühne entfernt, und stand man im Innenhof, so waren die Schauspieler wortwörtlich zum Greifen nahe. Die rechteckige Bühne ragte in den Zuschauerraum hinein (Apron Stage). Sie war etwa 15 Meter breit und 9 Meter tief. Im Gegensatz zum Innenhof war sie überdacht.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>John Donne (22. Januar 1572 – 31. März 1631) war ein englischer Schriftsteller und der bedeutendste der metaphysischen Dichter. Sein Werk umfasst Predigten, religiöse Gedichte, Übersetzungen aus dem Lateinischen, Epigramme, Elegien, Lieder und Sonette. Charakteristisch für Donnes Lyrik ist insbesondere seine Sakralisierung des Erotischen und die damit verbundene Entwicklung einer aus literaturgeschichtlicher Sicht provozierenden neuen Form der Liebeslyrik, in der insbesondere das körperliche Begehren und die Sexualität als heiliges Mysterium erscheinen. Neuartig ist dabei nicht so sehr seine Verwendung durchaus unkonventioneller religiöser Bilder oder Metaphern in einem erotischen Diskurs, sondern vor allem die Heiligsprechung der Liebe als körperlich-sexueller Erfahrung in einer Metaphorik und Bildersprache, die ans Blasphemische grenzt.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_DANTE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Dante Alighieri (1265 –  1321) war ein italienischer Dichter und Philosoph. Er überwand mit der in altitalienisch (bzw. toskanisch) verfassten Göttlichen Komödie das bis dahin dominierende Latein und führte das Italienische zu einer Literatursprache. Dante ist einer der bekanntesten Dichter der italienischen Literatur sowie des europäischen Mittelalters. Dantes Werk schöpft souverän aus der Theologie, der Philosophie und den übrigen Wissenschaften (Artes liberales) seiner Zeit. Es bezieht sich kunstvoll auf Vorbilder in der italienischen, provenzalischen, altfranzösischen und lateinischen Dichtung. Dante verbindet dabei Gelehrsamkeit und literarische Bildung mit einem hohen Maß an Eigenständigkeit in der gedanklichen Aneignung und im sprachlichen und poetischen Ausdruck. Wie kein anderer Dichter vor ihm stellt er die eigene Person als Liebender und Leidender, als Irrender und Lernender in den Mittelpunkt seiner Werke. Er spricht sich dabei nicht einfach selbst bekenntnishaft aus und macht sich nicht schlicht zum Chronisten seiner persönlichen Entwicklung, sondern stilisiert das Ich seiner Werke – deren lyrisches, erzählendes oder lehrhaftes Ich und die Erfahrung, die es zur Sprache bringt – nach Maßgabe genauer Wirkungsabsichten im Rahmen einer von Werk zu Werk fortentwickelten „Autofiktion“ (Hausmann). Er verbindet dieses Vorgehen mit dem hohen ethischen Anspruch, dem Leser, der politischen Gesellschaft und selbst der Kirche seiner Zeit einen Spiegel zur Selbsterkenntnis und ein Leitbild auf dem Weg zur Besserung zu bieten. Für ihn liegt das Ziel dieses Wegs im Persönlichen (ebenso wie im Politischen und Kirchenpolitischen) in der Übereinstimmung mit der göttlichen Weltordnung, wie sie nach seiner Überzeugung in der Bibel und ihrer inspirierten Auslegung durch die frühen Kirchenlehrer offenbart und zum Teil auch schon in den Werken der antiken Dichter (Vergil) und Philosophen (Aristoteles) vorgezeichnet ist.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_PEDIA_GREATPEOPLE_PAGE_GREAT_PERSON_INDIVIDUAL_CWON_MOLIERE_CHAPTER_HISTORY_PARA_1" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, alias Molière; (1622 – 1673) war ein französischer Schauspieler, Theaterdirektor und Dramatiker. Er gilt als einer der großen Klassiker und machte die Komödie zu einer der Tragödie potenziell gleichwertigen Gattung. Vor allem erhob er das Theater seiner Zeit zum Diskussionsforum über allgemeine menschliche Verhaltensweisen in der Gesellschaft. Molière ist ein Künstlername, den der Schauspieler und spätere Autor wohl ab 1643, spätestens jedoch seit Juni 1644 benutzte. Die Herkunft des Namens ist unklar, vielleicht stand eine gleichnamige südfranzösische Ortschaft Pate. Den Durchbruch erzielte Molière im November 1659 mit seiner in Prosa verfassten Komödie Les précieuses ridicules (Die lächerlichen feinen Damen), seinem ersten für ein überwiegend Pariser Publikum konzipierten Stück. Am Beispiel der beiden Protagonistinnen, zweier etwas exaltierter, möchte-gern-adelig und gebildet tuender Bürgermädchen, verspottet er hier die gekünstelte Sprechweise und die wirklichkeitsfremden Denkweisen der Preziösen, wie sie inzwischen auch im Bürgertum zu finden waren.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_2_NAME" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Lieder und Sonette</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_1_NAME" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Der Menschenfeind</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_1_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Niemand ist eine Insel, in sich ganz; jeder Mensch ist ein Stück des Kontinents, ein Teil des Festlandes. Jedes Menschen Tod ist mein Verlust, denn ich bin Teil der Menschheit; und darum verlange nie zu wissen, wem die Stunde schlägt; sie schlägt dir selbst.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_JOHN_DONNE_2_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Wie des Erdgrundes eng gewundene Bahn gallbitteres Salz aus Meereswasser siebt, so, schien mir, müßt ich meinen Wahn durch Reimnot plagen, bis er sich ergibt.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_2_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Der eine wartet, daß die Zeit sich wandelt, der andere packt sie kräftig an und handelt.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_DANTE_1_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Schwach ist die Liebe, die sich noch in Worten ausdrücken läßt.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_1_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Wie leicht doch bildet man sich eine falsche Meinung, geblendet vom Glanz der äußeren Erscheinung.</Text>
		</Replace>
		<Replace Tag="LOC_GREATWORK_CWON_MOLIERE_2_QUOTE" Language="de_DE">
			<Text>Man kann ein anständiger Mensch sein und doch schlechte Verse machen.</Text>
		</Replace>
	</LocalizedText>
</GameData>
